Guide to the Department of History Records, 1932-[ongoing] UA.25.23.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Administrative Files, 1932-1985, 22 boxes
  - Director of Graduate Studies, 1932-1983, bulk 1949-1983
    - Journal of Southern History membership applications, undated (Box 27)
    - M.A. Seminar paper requirement, undated (Box 27)
    - Master of Arts in Teaching, requirements satisfaction, undated (Box 27)
    - Organization of American Historians, undated (Box 27)
    - Placement forms, 1978-1979 (Box 27)
    - Southern Historical Association-Professional placement service, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Work Study, 1979, undated (Box 27)
    - Work Study-forms, undated (Box 27)
    - Alumni Office-History MAs and PhDs, 1975-1976 (Box 27)
    - Annual Reports to the Graduate Faculty from the Director of Graduate Studies, 1973-1976 (Box 27)
    - Assistantships, 1973-1974 (Box 27)
    - Awards, 1974-1978, 4 folders (Box 27)
    - Awards-new students (3 Folders), 1971-1974 (Box 27)
    - Awards-previously enrolled students (4 Folders), 1971-1975 (Box 27)
    - Awards-scholarships and fellowships, 1978-1979 (Box 27)
    - Awards-work study, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Awards and Fellowships, 1971 (Box 27)
    - Budget, 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - COIS-History Department, 1973 (Box 27)
    - Canadian Studies Program, 1973, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Careers, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Carolina Comments, 1971, 1973-1974 (Box 27)
    - Center for Commonwealth Studies, 1972-1975 (Box 27)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 27)
    - Chronological File, 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Correspondence to be answered, 1978-1979 (Box 27)
    - Correspondence-general, 1977 Aug.-1978 May (Box 27)
    - Correspondence with Graduate School, 1974 (Box 27)
    - Course Approvals, 1969-1977 (Box 27)
    - Courses, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Danforth Fellows, undated (Box 27)
    - Departmental Meetings, 1974 (Box 27)
    - Evaluation Meetings, 1978 (Box 27)
    - Executive Committee-Graduate Faculty, 1971-1976, 4 folders (Box 27)
    - Fellowship Applications, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Flyer Information, 1972-1975, undated (Box 27)
    - General Administrative information, 1969-1970 (Box 27)
    - Graduate Bulletin, 1973-1975, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Graduate Program Revisions, 1965-1974 (Box 28)
    - Graduate School, 1971-1974 (Box 28)
    - Graduate School Research Awards, 1973-1974 (Box 28)
    - Graduate Students who accepted, 1979-1980 (Box 28)
    - Inquiries, 1978-1979 (Box 28)
    - Job Roster, 1973-1974 (Box 28)
    - Lerner, Dr. Warren-correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 28)
    - Newsletter, 1974-1975 (Box 28)
    - Newsletter Info, 1976, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Newsletter Material, 1976-1977 (Box 28)
    - Newsletter, 1977 (Box 28)
    - Notices sent out, 1972-1975, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Placement File, 1974-1975 (Box 28)
    - Readerships, 1973-1975, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Southern Historical Association (SHA), 1973-1974 (Box 28)
    - SHA Breakfass, 1975-1979, 4 folders (Box 28)
    - Summer Awards, 1973-1975 (Box 28)
    - Travel Awards, 1974 (Box 28)
    - Trinity College Historical Society, 1969-1972 (Box 28)
    - Usual Letters, 1974 (Box 28)
  - Director of Undergraduate Studies, 1957-1977
    Contains material created and accumulated by the departmental Director of Undergraduate Studies and consists of correspondence and memoranda concerning topics such as courses, curriculum, registration and scheduling of courses, honors and independent study, and material collected for undergraduate bulletins. Also present are minutes from various committees such as Committee on Courses, History Undergraduate Majors, Curriculum Committee, and the Executive Committee. A majority of the material was accumulated during the long tenure of Frederic B.M. Hollyday; but also includes material accumulated by Joel Colton, Robert Durden, Theodore Ropp, and Stephen A. Young.
    - Academic Guide for Freshmen, 1973-1974 (Box 28)
    - Advanced Placement, 1962-1968, 1970-1974, 6 folders (Box 28)
    - Advising, 1971, undated (Box 28)
    - Ancient History, 1973 (Box 28)
    - B.S. in History, 1973 (Box 28)
    - Bulletin, 1971-1977, 7 folders (Box 28)
    - Bulletin-final copy, 1975-1976 (Box 28)
    - Bulletin-prospective students, 1968-1971 (Box 28)
    - Careers and Advisors, 1974-1975 (Box 28)
    - Catalogue and Curriculum revisions, 1966-1970 (Box 28)
    - Colton Material, 1962-1965 (Box 28)
    - Committee on Courses, 1972-1974 and 7 March 1973, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Committee on Courses, 1974-1976 April, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Committee of History Undergraduate Majors (CHUM), 1968-1970, 1974-1976, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - Comparative Area Studies, 1972, undated (Box 29)
    - Course Approval, Committee on Course of Instruction, 1971-1972 (Box 29)
    - Course Electives-transfer credit, 1971-1972 (Box 29)
    - Course Preferences, 1973-1978, 1972-1976, 5 folders (Box 29)
    - Course Requests, 1973-1974 (Box 29)
    - Courses, 1973-1976 (Box 29)
    - Course Scheduling Preferences, 1974-1975 (Box 29)
    - Cross-listed course-Religion, 1973-1974 (Box 29)
    - Curriculum Committee, Small-Group Learning Experience, 1972-1973 (Box 29)
    - Departmental Meeting, 1972 Sept. 8 (Box 29)
    - Departmental Meeting-minutes, 1974 Sept. 6 (Box 29)
    - Departmental Meeting-report, 1975-1976 (Box 29)
    - Director Calendar, 1975-1976 (Box 29)
    - Double Majors, 1972 (Box 29)
    - Durden and Ropp material, 1960-1962 (Box 29)
    - Executive Committee, 1975 Sept.-Nov. (Box 29)
    - Executive Committee membership, 1973-1974 (Box 29)
    - Faculty Scholars Nominations, 1975 (Box 29)
    - Fall Schedule 1972, 1971 October (Box 29)
    - Fellowship Awards, 1973 (Box 29)
    - Final Registration, 1975 (Box 29)
    - Final Schedules, 1973-1975 (Box 29)
    - Freshman-Sophomore Seminars, 1971 (Box 29)
    - Freshman Credit for History 1-2, principles, 1971 October (Box 29)
    - Freshman Guide, 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Freshmen in U.S. History, 1973 (Box 29)
    - Gentzler, Prof. J. Mason, History 142, 1971 October (Box 29)
    - Handout Drafts, 1973-1974 (Box 29)
    - Handouts and Major Meetings, 1973 March, undated (Box 29)
    - Handouts for Major Meetings, 1974-1976 (Box 29)
    - History 1-2, 1971 October (Box 29)
    - History 1-2 Rooms, final exam, 1966 (Box 29)
    - History 105 Survey, 1971-1972 (Box 29)
    - History 191, 1972 March-April (Box 29)
    - History 191s and 2s, 1971-1972 (Box 29)
    - History 195X, 1971 August (Box 29)
    - History 195-196 Seminar, 1972-1974 (Box 29)
    - History 199 1DC, 1971, 1972 (Box 29)
    - History Course Handbook, 1974-1975 (Box 29)
    - History Majors, 1968, 1970-1972, 4 folders (Box 29)
    - Honors
      - 1970, 1972-1976, 5 folders (Box 29)
      - Candidates, 1973-1974 (Box 29)
      - Honors Letter, 1973 Feb. (Box 29)
      - Procedures (past), 1971-1976 (Box 29)
      - Programs, 1968-1971 (Box 29)
    - Independent Study
      - 1973-1976, 7 folders (Box 29)
      - Faculty credit, 1973-1975 (Box 29)
      - Housing, 1972 March 23 (Box 29)
      - Procedures, 1973 (Box 29)
      - Programs, 1968-1971 (Box 29)
      - Survey, 1974 (Box 29)
    - Inquiries, 1971-1972 October, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Inquiries and Miscellaneous, 1971-1976 May, 4 folders (Box 29)
    - Institute of European Studies (Vienna), 1976 (Box 29)
    - Institute of Policy Sciences, 1971 Nov. 12 (Box 29)
    - Interdisciplinary Programs, 1967-1969 (Box 29)
    - Lampe, Fred, manuscript, 1975 (Box 29)
    - Living-Learning Courses, 1968-1969 (Box 29)
    - Majors Committee, 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Majors Meeting, 1972-1975, 6 folders (Box 30)
    - Majors Requirement, 1974 (Box 30)
    - "The Major Step," 1973-1975 (Box 30)
    - Methodology, 1971 Oct., undated (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1981, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous Personalia, 1970-1975 (Box 30)
    - New Curriculum, 1968-1969 (Box 30)
    - N.C. State and UNC Coordinator, 1973-1974 (Box 30)
    - Not advanced history courses, 1971 (Box 30)
    - Obsolete Courses, 1963-1978 (Box 30)
    - Obsolete Registration, 1963-1966 (Box 30)
    - Permission for Courses, 1968-1969 (Box 30)
    - Policy-AP transfer, 1975 (Box 30)
    - Preregistration and registration, 1964-1971 (Box 30)
    - Preregistration, 1970-1972, 1974, 5 folders (Box 30)
    - Procedures and Principles, 1966-1969 (Box 30)
    - Program II, course of study, 1969-1971 (Box 30)
    - Programming, 1963-1965, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - Registration
      - 1963-1964, 1970-1976, 11 folders (Box 30)
      - Registration and Majors Meeting, 1972 Oct. (Box 30)
      - Registration Reminders, 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 30)
      - Registration Reminders-corrections, 1973 (Box 30)
      - Registration Reminders and 1974 Draft, 1973-1974 (Box 30)
    - Retired Records, 1973 (Box 30)
    - Schedule, 1970-1976, 6 folders (Box 30)
    - Schedule-preparation for final copy, 1974-1975 (Box 30)
    - Scheduling and Placement, 1965-1970 (Box 30)
    - Scheduling, 1966 (Box 30)
    - Scheduling-policy, 1972 Sept. (Box 30)
    - Scheduling-preferences, 1972-1975, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - Scheduling course in dormitories, 1972 (Box 30)
    - Senior Theses and Honors, 1971-1972 (Box 30)
    - Spring Schedule (1973), 1972 Sept. (Box 30)
    - Statistics, 1957-1976, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Student Evaluation form, 1971, undated (Box 30)
    - Study Abroad, 1968-1970 (Box 30)
    - Study of the Curriculum, 1975 (Box 30)
    - Teacher-Course evaluations, 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - Time Schedule Preferences, 1973-1976, 3 folders (Box 31)
    - Tutorials, 1973 Feb. (Box 31)
    - Undergrad Bulletin-preliminary copy, 1974-1975 (Box 31)
    - Undergrad Bulletin-history copy, 1974-1975 (Box 31)
    - Undergrad Requirements, 1974 Feb. (Box 31)
    - Undergraduate Faculty Council of the Arts and Sciences, 1968-1972, 3 folders (Box 31)
    - Undergrad Students, schedule, 1970 Nov. (Box 31)
    - Undergraduate Teacher Education at Duke, 1968-1969 (Box 31)
    - Urban Studies, undated (Box 31)
    - Varieties of Learning Experience-report, 1968 (Box 31)
    - Woodrow Wilson Fellowship, 1968 (Box 31)
    - Young, Charles R., 1970 (Box 31)
- Inactive Faculty Files, 1952-1984
  Name files that contain correspondence, memos, and various other communication with faculty members concerning sabbatical leave, current research projects, departmental promotions, nominations for various research grants, fellowships, and awards, recommendations for teaching positions as well as curriculum vitae and professional biographies. Files of long-term faculty also contain obituaries and funeral service programs. Files are arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Acomb, Francis D., 1959-1974, 1984 (Box 31)
  - Askew, William, 1970 (Box 31)
  - Bailey, Thomas A., 1952 (Box 31)
  - Barnes, Donald G., 1962-1964 (Box 31)
  - Beachey, R.W., 1965-1967 (Box 31)
  - Blassingame, John, 1969 (Box 31)
  - Broadfoot, William (Flowers Collection), 1957-1964, 1970 (Box 31)
  - Carroll, E. Malcolm, 1960-1961, 1969-1971 (Box 31)
  - Chang, Peter (Chinese-Japanese Language Instruction), 1967-1968 (Box 31)
  - Cracraft, James E., 1969 (Box 31)
  - Curtiss, John S., 1959-1984 (Box 31)
  - De, Borum, 1965-1966, 1973 (Box 31)
  - Dray, William F., 1973 (Box 31)
  - Dunn, Patrick, 1969 (Box 31)
  - Furley, O.W., 1965-1971 (Box 31)
  - Galbraith, John, 1959-1961 (Box 31)
  - Godfrey, James L., 1980-1981 (Box 31)
  - Greeman, Betty Dix, 1972-1974 (Box 31)
  - Hagerman, Edward, 1964-1965 (Box 31)
  - Hamilton, William B., 1953, 1960-1972 (Box 31)
  - Hartwig, Gerald H., 1969-1982 (Box 31)
  - Hollyday, Frederic B.M., 1961-1982 (Box 31)
  - Harrison, John, 1962 (Box 31)
  - Henrick, Joseph, 1969 (Box 31)
  - Ikai, Teruko, 1969 (Box 31)
  - Islam Ul, Zafar, 1962-1963 (Box 31)
  - Jones, David, 1966 (Box 31)
  - Keppel-Jones, Arthur, 1962-1964 (Box 31)
  - Kessinger, Tom G., 1972-1973 (Box 31)
  - Lanning, John Tate, 1958-1976 (Box 31)
  - Laprade, William T., 1977-1979 (Box 31)
  - Lin, Paul (Japanese Language), 1971 (Box 31)
  - Manchester, Alan K., 1961-1963 (Box 31)
  - Mansergh, Nicholas, 1961-1965 (Box 31)
  - Marder, Arthur J., 1961-1963 (Box 31)
  - Marshall, Dorothy, 1963-1967 (Box 31)
  - Nelson, Ernest William, 1964-1975, 1980 (Box 31)
  - Raychaudhuri, Tapan, 1963-1969 (Box 31)
  - Rolf, Robert, 1971-1977 (Box 31)
  - Sablinsky, Walter, 1969 (Box 31)
  - Starr, S. Frederick (candidate), 1969 (Box 31)
  - Stevens, Harry, 1955-1957, 1963 (Box 31)
  - Stokes, Eric (Commonwealth), 1961-1962 (Box 31)
  - Swan, Robert, 1961 (Box 31)
  - Tischendorf, Alfred, 1955, 1960-1963 (Box 31)
  - Wallace, James C., 1962-1963 (Box 31)
  - Wallace, Lillian Parker, 1971 (Box 31)
  - Whiteside, Andrew G., 1954 (Box 31)
  - Winks, Robin W., 1960-1964 (Box 31)
  - Woody, Robert, 1967-1970 (Box 31)
- Nixon Library Files, 1981-1982, 1 boxes
  Contains material relating to the department of history's activities surrounding the possible location of the Richard Nixon Presidential Library at Duke University. The material consists of faculty and alumni correspondence, correspondence with President Terry Sanford, university memoranda, meeting minutes, and various clippings from newspapers and periodicals, both local and national. The Nixon Archives and Library was to be situated adjacent to campus on land provided by Duke University. The building was to be the property of the U.S. government, administered and directed by the National Archives Referral Service, and house the Nixon presidential papers and tapes. Material is arranged chronologically and spans a brief period from August 1981 through March 1982.
  - 1981, August 11-31 (Box 32)
  - 1981, September 1-14 (Box 32)
  - 1981, September 15-December (Box 32)
  - 1982, January-March, undated (Box 32)
- External Review Files, 1993-2000, 1 boxes
  Contains correspondence, memoranda, reports and other materials created during an external review of the Department carried out in 1999-2000. The files include reports prepared by various departmental officers for the review team, a copy of the final report and responses, and files from a 1994 Departmental review.
  - Current, 2000 (Box 33)
  - Final Report, 2000 May-August (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous Reports, 1993-2000 (Box 33)
  - Responses, 2000 (Box 33)
- Transcripts: Oral History Techniques, 1973-1974, 1 boxes
  Transcripts from twenty-six oral history interviews held by students with faculty, staff, and students concerning contemporary race relations at Duke University from History 279: Oral History Techniques taught by Dr. Larry Goodwyn. Interviews without release forms are restricted; they may be consulted for information only. Copying, citation, quotation, or publication of the restricted interviews is prohibited without the written permission of the interview subject. Unless otherwise noted all interviews were conducted in 1974.
  - Beck, Judy and Peggy Phelps (Box 34)
  - Branch, Walter (Box 34)
  - Bryan, Jay (Box 34)
  - Carr, Thomas (Box 34)
  - Cockrell, David (Box 34)
  - Cook, Samuel (Box 34)
  - Corders, Maurice (Box 34)
  - Duh, Sam (Box 34)
  - Ganaway, Eddie and Al Broussard (Box 34)
  - Harris, Ann and Karen Hammett (Box 34)
  - Lerner, Joel and Alphine W. Jefferson (Box 34)
  - Morris, Brent S. and David M. Lacey (Box 34)
  - Saleem, Wanda and Pam Pasco (Box 34)
  - Spelling, Carol (Box 34)
  - Williams, Chuck (Box 34)
  - Wilson, Moultrie and Richard Melcher (Box 34)
  - Unidentified black worker (Box 34)
  - Unidentified student (Box 34)
  - Unidentified student, 1973 (Box 34)